Guide to the Thomas Thweatt Jones papers, 1757-1979 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Thomas Thweatt Jones papers 1757-1979 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jones, Thomas Thweatt, 1906-1991
6.5 Linear Feet Approx. 8100 Items
Physician and resident of Durham, North Carolina.
Collection consists of correspondence (chiefly 1947-1974), writings, reports, printed material, clippings, and other papers, relating to Jones's interest as a physician in alcoholism, mental health, and agathanasia (the care of the dying), and his activities with the Durham Council on Alcoholism and Medical Society of the state of North Carolina. There are also letters, photographs, writings, legal and financial papers, and other items relating to the Jones, Scanlun, Blackwell, and Graver families of North Carolina and Virginia (Dinwiddie County and other places). Collection highlights include a memoir of Rev. George White discussing slave-owner relations prior to and during the Civil War; photographs of Shenandoah Normal College (Reliance, Va.); records of Jones's service on the staff of the 65th General Hospital in England during World War II (affiliated with the Duke School of Medicine); Mrs. Jones's high school scrapbook and her journals of 1923 and 1926 trips abroad; and a photograph album and other scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Thweatt Jones papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1974-1975 and 1987.
Biographical Note
Thomas Thweatt Jones, whose family was originally from Dinwiddie County, Virginia, was born in Newport News, Virginia in 1906 to Robert Randolph Jones and Sallie B. Jones. He married Mary Cuyler Scanlon. Jones passed away in 1991 in Jacksonville, Alabama.
Collection Overview
The Thomas Thweatt Jones papers consist of correspondence (chiefly 1947-1974), writings, memoranda, reports, printed material, clippings, and other papers, relating to Jones's interest as a physician in alcoholism, mental health, and agathanasia (the care of the dying), and his activities with the Durham Council on Alcoholism and Medical Society of the state of North Carolina. There are also letters, photographs, writings, legal and financial papers, and other items relating to the Jones, Scanlun, Blackwell, and Graver families history and genealogy.
Collection highlights include a memoir of Rev. George White discussing slave-owner relations prior to and during the Civil War; photographs of Shenandoah Normal College (Reliance, Va.) students and faculty; personal correspondence; clippings and printed publications dealing with alcoholism and agathanasia, a term Dr. Jones adopted referring to a patient's right to die; records of Jones's service on the staff of the 65th General Hospital during World War II; Mrs. Jones's high school scrapbook; a photograph album; journals of her 1923 and 1926 trips abroad; and genealogical materials, including a sketch by Dr. Jones of his brother, Dr. Robert R. Jones, Jr., one of the original staff members of Duke Hospital. Robert Jones was killed in 1941 by a patient.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Jones, Thomas Thweatt, 1906-1991
Jones family (N.C.)
Jones family (Va.)
White, George
Shenandoah Normal College -- History
United States. Army. General Hospital, 65th
Alcoholism -- North Carolina
Alcoholism -- Treatment
Euthanasia
Mental health -- North Carolina
Physicians -- Correspondence
Physicians -- North Carolina -- Durham
Right to die
Slavery -- United States -- History
World War, 1939-1945 -- Hospitals
Dinwiddie County (Va.) -- History
North Carolina -- Genealogy
North Carolina -- History
Virginia -- Genealogy
Virginia -- History
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Thomas Thweatt Jones papers, 1757-1979 and undated, (39 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
  - Biographical and autobiographical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1830-1930 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1950 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962, Sept. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1962, Oct.-1964, (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1979 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 11)
  - Addresses and writings, 1928-1963, (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Addresses and writings, 1964-1973 and undated (Box 12)
  - Addresses and writings, undated (Box 13)
  - Addresses and writings by persons other than Jones, 1875-1943 and undated (Box 13)
  - Memoranda and reports, 1942-1971, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Memos and reports: Alcoholism, 1953-1971 (Box 14)
  - Memos and reports: Alcoholism, 1972-1974 and undated (Box 15)
  - Memos and reports: Mental health, 1954-1974 and undated (Box 16)
  - Memos and reports: Watts Hospital, 1957-1972 (Box 16)
  - Memos and reports: First Presbyterian Church, 1956-1972 and undated (Box 17)
  - Memos and reports: Duke Medical Center, 1964-1972 and undated (Box 17)
  - Legal papers, 1757-1974 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Financial papers, 1818-1970, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Genealogy, (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Printed material, 1896-1958, (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - Printed material, 1959-1963 (Box 20)
  - Printed material, 1964-1979 (Box 21)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 22)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, 1947-1963 (Box 22)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, 1961-1964 (Box 23)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, 1965-1968 (Box 24)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, 1969-1973 (Box 25)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, 1974-1975 and undated (Box 26)
  - Printed material: Alcoholism, undated (Box 27)
  - Printed material: Mental Health, 1963-1974 (Box 27)
  - Printed material: Mental health, 1963-1974 (Box 28)
  - Printed material: Mental health, undated (Box 29)
  - Photographs: Blackwell and Graver families, St. Paul's, and miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 29)
  - Photographs: Jones and Scanlon families, El Paso, National Council on Alcoholism, and various persons (Box 30)
  - Photographs: Jones Family, Cora O'Briant, Hage Military Academy, Duke University, El Paso High School, Presbyterian Church at Newport News, Wright Machinery Company, Department of Mental Health (Box 31)
  - Clippings, 1887-1965 (Box 32)
  - Clippings, 1966-1979 and undated (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1901-1970 (Box 34)
  - Questionnaires on Alcoholism (Box 34)
  - Volumes (Box 35)
  - Volumes (Box 36)
  - Volumes, print, journals, scrapbook (Box 37)
  - Volumes, Aline McKenzie, (3 scrapbooks) (Box 38)
  - Through the Years with the Durham Council on Alcoholism, 1956-1963 (Box 39)
  - Scrapbook, 1860-1943 (Box 39)
  - Map of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, 1878 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Legal documents, 1794 and 1788 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Group photographs, Shenandoah Normal College, Virginia, 1890-1904 (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession 1987, (1 box)
  - Unprocessed materials including papers, printed material, correspondence, handwritten notes, clippings, and materials relating to the Durham Rescue Mission and Jacob's Ladder. (Box 1)